So let's turn to today's דף Daf *daf*, דף י׳ *daf yud*,
and we pick up literally at the very beginning, the very top
of דף י׳ עמוד א׳ *daf yud amud aleph*. The issue here
had been that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was in a long discussion
about whether a לחי lechi. *lechi* that is visible from the outside
of the חצר chatzer. *chatzer* or the מבוי mavoi, *mavoi* but not
on the inside, whether that's legitimate or not. And one of the
challenges had been to prove that it was not acceptable was the
classic case we've been dealing with for the last few days about
the small courtyard that opens up into the big one, that the
small one is considered to be fully exposed and therefore you can't
carry in the small one. And the question had been, well why
is the small one fully exposed? Why isn't the fact that it
extends beyond—here we have this picture here—why isn't the fact that it
extends beyond, why aren't those considered like לחיים *lechis* that are visible
from the outside? And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is well the
walls go all the way in so therefore there's nothing that extends
beyond. So then the question is okay but if it's within three
טפחים tfachim. *tefachim* because we had said this was ten אמות amot
*amot* and this was eleven אמות amot. *amot*, so there's three טפחים
tfachim *tefachim* on each side, let's say לבוד lavud. *lavud* and that
should be just as good. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says well no
it's not evenly divided. There's two טפחים tfachim *tefachim* here and four
טפחים tfachim. *tefachim* here, so here you can say לבוד lavud *lavud*
but not here, it only extends on one side. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* said okay but so what, one side should be enough,
normally we say one לחי lechi. *lechi* is enough for a courtyard.
And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues on the top of י׳
עמוד א׳ *yud amud aleph*, רבי Rebbi היא *Rebbi hi*, this is
the position of רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*, דאמר בעינן שני פסין *de-amar beinon
shenei passin*, he says you need actually two planks. Now this is
not normally by a מבוי mavoi, *mavoi* but it is by a
חצר chatzer *chatzer*. I'm not going to go into detail here, we're
going to unpack this more in another day or two, but you
might remember this from the beginning of the מסכת *masechet* that we
sort of said that a מבוי mavoi, *mavoi* is with a לחי
lechi. *lechi* and a חצר chatzer *chatzer* might be with actually a
plank or with two planks one on each side and that in
the end the real difference between a מבוי mavoi, *mavoi* and a
חצר chatzer. *chatzer* was less how it was functioning and more whether
it was more long than it was—if it was more like lengthwise
it was a מבוי mavoi, *mavoi*, if it was more wider than
it was long it was a חצר chatzer *chatzer*. So we'll worry
about those specifics later, right now we're saying that because we're talking
here about a חצר chatzer *chatzer*, that's why you actually need something
on each side. רבי היא דאמר בעינן שני פסין *Rebbi hi de-amar
beinon shenei passin*, you need two planks, one on each side and
therefore you don't have it here, you only have it on one
side because you're only saying לבוד lavud *lavud* on one side. So
all of this is to deal with the problem about why doesn't
it count as a לחי lechi *lechi* since it's visible from the
outside if you say לבוד lavud. *lavud*. דתניא *de-tanya*, we taught in
a ברייתא Braitah *Baraita* and again we'll see this in two days,
חצר chatzer ניתרת בפס אחת *chatzer niteret be-pas achat*, a
חצר chatzer *chatzer* is made permissible with one plank in the area
that's exposed to the רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim *reshut ha-rabbim*, רבי אומר
בשני פסין *Rebbi omer bishnei passin* and רבי *Rebbi* says two planks.
So we'll see that and how that compares to a מבוי mavoi
*mavoi* later but for now that's our answer. So the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* says האי מאי *hai mai*, what are you talking about, what
type of an answer is that? אי אמרת בשלמא נראה מבחוץ ושוה
מבפנים אינו נידון משום לחי nira mibachutz v'shaveh mibifnim eino nidon mishum
lechi. *Ei amrit bishlama nira mi-bachutz ve-shaveh mi-bifnim einu nidon mishum lechi*,
if we go back to what we'd always been assuming that something
that's visible from the outside but flush on the inside does not
have the status of a לחי lechi. *lechi*, so then all this
idea of one חצר chatzer *chatzer* opening into the other makes sense.
And ורבי סבר לה *ve-Rebbi savar lah*, we'll also say that רבי
*Rebbi* holds כרבי יוסי *ke-Rabbi Yose*, like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*. Now
what's the position of רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*? רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*'s
a position that says that each plank has to be three טפחים
tfachim. *tefachim* wide. Okay we'll see why that matters in a minute.
ודרבי זירא ודרבינא ליתא *ve-de-Rabbi Zeira ve-de-Ravina lessa*, we'll dump רבי זירא
*Rabbi Zeira* and רבינא *Ravina*. רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* and רבינא *Ravina*
were the ones that said the special case with the walls extending
in and that it's four on one side two on the other,
forget all of that. If we went back to the way everything
was explained normally which makes sense, okay
then you have—then the fact that it's visible from the outside doesn't
matter, this smaller חצר chatzer *chatzer* is totally exposed. Now what's this
idea of רבי *Rebbi* holding like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*? Because we
understand why the smaller חצר chatzer *chatzer*'s a problem. Why is the
bigger חצר chatzer *chatzer* okay? The bigger חצר chatzer *chatzer*'s okay is
because it's you know it's only an opening, it's not the entire
wall. But it's opening because you have wall on each side. Now
רבי *Rebbi*, if
רבי *Rebbi* normally says that a חצר chatzer *chatzer* to be okay
needs a wall coming in here on each side, two פסים *passim*,
two planks, how big does each plank have to be? Well רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yose* says each plank has to be three טפחים tfachim
*tefachim*. This is a normal חצר chatzer *chatzer* to be okay for
רבי *Rebbi*. Well that's this חצר chatzer, *chatzer* up here. It's got
something going in on each side. How long would each side have
to be? Three טפחים tfachim *tefachim*. So if each side had to
be three טפחים tfachim *tefachim*, remember we said that the big חצר
chatzer *chatzer* was ten אמות amot *amot* and the larger חצר chatzer
*chatzer* was eleven אמות amot, *amot*, so now we understand why we
described it that way. In this—it has to be one אמה amah
*amah* more so you have three טפחים tfachim *tefachim* on each side
so the big חצר chatzer *chatzer* is okay. makes sense. Small חצר
chatzer, no good, totally open. The fact that it has this stuff
on the side is not relevant for the small חצר. chatzer Big
חצר chatzer is okay because it's got something going in on each
side, and each thing is three טפחים. tfachim. And that means the
big חצר chatzer is one אמה amah bigger than the small חצר.
chatzer So that makes sense. So then ודרב זירא ודרב אמי ליתא,
ve-de-Rav Zeira ve-de-Rav Ami leisa, it doesn't hold of Rav Zeira and
Rav Ami. It doesn't have the walls extending in. משום הכי mishum
hachi and that's why the case is described as קטנה בעשר, ketanah
be-eser, the small חצר chatzer is 10 אמות amot, wide, that's the
maximum opening that you could be dealing with because bigger than that
would be too big of an opening for the big one. וגדולה
באחת עשרה u-gedolah be-achas esrei and the big one is in 11
אמות. amot משום mishum and now it explains itself again, דרבי סבירא
ליה כרבי יוסי, de-Rabbi sevira lei ke-Rabbi Yosi,
because Rabbi holds like Rabbi Yosi. So the simple case is this
is the case, small חצר chatzer. is no good because it's totally
open. The fact that it has those things on the side and
you can see it from the outside isn't relevant from the perspective
of the small חצר totally open. Big חצר is okay. Why? Because
this opening does not exceed 10 אמות amot? and because it's got
a plank on each side which is at least three טפחים tfachim
big. So that makes this one אמה amah, bigger, three and three
טפחים tfachim. is one אמה, amah so that makes this one אמה
amah bigger. The case makes complete sense if we say it that
way. אלא, ela, but אי אמרת נראה מבחוץ ושווה מבפנים נידון משום
לחי, ei amart nireh mi-bachutz ve-shaveh mi-bifnim nidon mishum lechi,
if we say like we were saying yesterday that we have to
try to explain that when it is visible from the outside it
counts as a לחי. lechi And then we had a whole problem,
why isn't the small חצר okay? The small חצר also has a
לחי. lechi ודרב זירא ודרב אמי איתא, ve-de-Rav Zeira ve-de-Rav Ami isa,
so what we had the first thing we had to say to
explain why this was not okay, that it didn't have these things
on the side, is we said what Rav Zeira and Rav Ami
said, that the walls extended in. So it didn't have anything on
the side. But then we were bothered with the idea of לבוד.
lavud. To get out of לבוד lavud we said that it's two
and four here, so you only say לבוד lavud. on one side.
That's how we explained it yesterday. If you say that ורבי לא
סבירא ליה כרבי יוסי ve-Rabbi lo sevira lei ke-Rabbi Yosi and Rabbi
does not hold of Rabbi Yosi who says that, but now we've
got a problem. What problem do we have? If this is the
scenario, two and four, why is the big חצר good? The big
חצר is good because it's got a wall coming in on each
side. But here this wall's only two טפחים. tfachim. Rabbi Yosi says
the wall that comes in on each side for Rabbi has to
be three טפחים. tfachim So it must be Rabbi doesn't hold of
Rabbi Yosi. Rabbi allows even less than three טפחים tefachim to count
as a wall. So the big חצר is good because you have
wall on each side, even less than three טפחים tefachim. is okay.
The small חצר is no good because you only have a wall
on one side. If that's what you're trying to claim ורבי לא
סבירא ליה כרבי יוסי, ve-Rabbi lo sevira lei ke-Rabbi Yosi, Rabbi doesn't
hold of Rabbi Yosi.
So we get why this case is okay. The big one has
walls on both sides, the small one only has a wall on
one side based on לבוד. lavud, But what we don't get is
why you had to say precisely that the case was 11 and
10. So if that's true, גדולה באחת עשרה למה לי, gedolah be-achas
esrei lamah li, why do you have to describe that the big
one was 11 אמות, amot? one אמה amah more than the small
one? Like the first way we understood, you had to get one
אמה amah more so you had three טפחים Tefachim on each side.
But here what's the point of explaining that the big one is
exactly one אמה amah bigger than the small one? ממילא, mimeila, make
up your mind,
אי משום דגדולה קאתי, ei mishum de-gedolah ka-asi, if you're trying to
explain what is minimal needed to make the top one okay, בעשר
ושני טפחים סגי. be-eser ve-shnei tfachim sagi. So
in the other scenario where before we got all this green stuff
we understood why you had to say 11, so that each side
was three טפחים tefachim which was the minimum amount that you needed
for the plank. But here we're saying you don't need three for
the plank because this side is okay because of this one. So
why do we have to give the scenario that this is one
אמה amah bigger? What would be required if we were focusing on
the top one? If this is 10 אמות, amot, how big would
the top one have to be for the top one to be
okay? It would just have to be 10 אמות amot. and two
טפחים. tefachim Right? You wouldn't need to be a whole אמה amah
bigger, just a little bit extra would have been okay
if you're not holding of Rabbi Yosi.
If you're not holding of Rabbi Yosi, why would you have to
explain that this was a whole אמה amah bigger? So if you
wanted to say the minimum criteria to make the big one okay
then it would be
אי משום דגדולה קאתי בעשר ושני טפחים סגי, ei mishum de-gedolah ka-asi
be-eser ve-shnei tfachim sagi, 10 אמה amah and two טפחים tefachim. would
be enough. ואי למפסל קטנה קאתי ve-ei le-mipsel ketanah ka-asi and if
you want to explain why the small one was no good, because
the point is in order to explain why this is no good
we have to explain that one of the sides, right, is bigger
than 10 טפחים. Is that how you say bigger than three? Bigger
than three טפחים. Right. If one of the sides is bigger than
three טפחים to explain why the small one is no good so
you can't say לבוד. lavud But if that's what you're trying to
explain why the small one is no good, why did he give
precisely a case that it's eleven אמות? amot Why not give a
more extreme case that it's, you know, that it's much larger the
other one, so that there's no way you could think of saying
לבוד lavud by the small one.
Where do we actually get the dimensions of this case? What? Where
do we actually get the dimensions of this case?
It was at the ברייתא braita quoted yesterday, where we say קטנה
בעשר גדולה באחת עשרה. ketanah be-eser gedolah be-achas rei. Three lines from
the bottom in the דף ד' עמוד ב'. daf daled amud bet.
ואילי מצריך לקטן כהאי, ve-ilu mitzreich lekatan kehai, and if you're giving
the dimensions
to explain
why the
small one
is no good, לשמעינן דנפיק טפי. letsmin d'mipok tuvei.
Why did you give an example of eleven אמות? amot Say that
the big one is like twenty אמות, amot. you know, so that
there's no possibility that you're saying לבוד. lavud אלא לאו שמע מינה,
Ella lav shema mina,
from all of this we can infer, נראה מבחוץ ושוה מבפנים אינו
נידון משום לחי. nidon mishum lechi.
That if it's visible from the outside and not from the inside,
it doesn't count as a לחי. lechi. שמע מינה. Shema mina. That
is a good proof. So to sort of summarize what the גמרא
gemara said is we have this case,
the question was why is this חצר a problem if these are
visible from this direction? And that should prove that the fact that
it's visible from the outside doesn't count.
That was a pretty good proof.
So yesterday what the גמרא Gemara, tried to do is it tried
to make a very special case and say the walls extended up
here, and what about the fact that you should be able to
say לבוד, lavud? so it says you can say לבוד lavud. on
one side, but you can't say לבוד Lavud on the other side,
and that's why this is a problem. But then the גמרא Gemara
basically said, if that was the case, we would not have explained
it exactly as eleven אמות. amot, If the point was to say
that you can't say לבוד lavud. here, that's why this is a
problem, why did you give us such a narrow definition that I
might think that you would say לבוד? lavud. You should have just
explained that it was much larger and there was no possibility of
saying לבוד. So the fact that you explained the case of eleven
אמות amot, and ten אמות amot. makes it clear that that's not
what that case is about. And therefore, you see that it is
not that special case you were trying to describe. Yes, Charlie.
So,
by being
aligned with the wall, that aligned with the wall according to the
viewpoint of someone inside the small חצר, but it's still okay in
the large חצר because one sees the little...
Yeah, from the large חצר it's okay because it's visible from within
the large.
So that means you'd have to put a real לחי lechi, inside
the
small one for the small one to be okay. So at the
end of the day, the way we explain this case is forget
the special case, it's a simple case of a large חצר and
a big חצר, and the reason that we said one אמה amah
bigger is because the larger one is an אמה amah bigger to
put three טפחים on each side and that's the position of רבי
who says for this חצר for it to have two walls on
each side, each one has to be three טפחים. Then it makes
total sense why we're saying this is exactly one אמה amah bigger
than this. So this has a wall of sufficient size on each
side. But if it was this whole crazy special case where the
walls go in and so on, it would not have explained why
we said that it's exactly one אמה Ama. bigger.
If you don't hold like רבי then you don't need it to
be ten or eleven אמות.
amot, Yeah, but the case, if it was given as the example
of ten and eleven אמות, amot, then there's no way to explain
it except that way. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So it seems like that's the conclusion, but the גמרא Gemara
is not yet done. Okay. אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. So
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, לא שמיע לי האי שמעתתא. lo shamia
leh hai shemaitah. I didn't hear, and now רב יוסף Rav Yosef
forgot his teachings and he forgot his learning, then he said, you
know,
I didn't hear this teaching in the name of רב הונה Rav
Huna that we've been saying until now that if it's visible from
the outside it counts as a לחי. lechi אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye who was רב יוסף Rav
Yosef's student said to him, את אמרת ניהלן, at amart niah lan,
what do you mean? You told it to us, this position of
רב הונה. Rav Huna.
והא אמרת ניהלן, ve-ha amart niah lan, and regarding the following discussion
you told it to us. דאמר רמי בר אבא אמר רב הונה,
De-amar Rami bar Abba amar Rav Huna, again a statement in the
name of רב הונה, Rav Huna, לחי המושך עם דופנו של מבוי
פחות מארבע אמות נידון משום לחי ומשתמש בחורו הפנימי ארבע אמות נידון
משום מבוי ואסור להשתמש בכולן.
lechi hamoshech im dofno shel mavoi pachas m'arbah amot nidon mishum lechi
u-mishtamesh be-churo hapnimu arbah
amot nidon mishum mavoi ve-asur le-ishtamesh bekulan. So if you have a
לחי lechi that stretches out from the מבוי, mavoi.
which basically רש"י Rashi says is, again, if this is the thickness
of the מבוי, mavoi what would be a good example? Yeah, just
this. Okay, and you have something that extends like this, right? It
extends... I'm sorry, it extends like this. Okay, you sort of see
that? It extends... so it's from the inside of it...
you have here is the thickness of the wall, here's your מבוי,
mavoi. okay, and you have a לחי lechi, that goes like this.
So if I'm standing within the מבוי, mavoi right, it looks like
it's just an extension of the wall. From outside of the מבוי,
mavoi you see that it's a לחי. lechi Another perfect example of
being visible from the outside and not from the inside. So what
was the הלכה? halacha? The הלכה halacha was the following. Let's read
it again. So, לחי המושך
עם דופנו של מבוי,
lechi hamoshech
im dofno shel mavoi, it extends with the wall of the מבוי
mavoi, from the
inside. פחות מארבע אמות, pachot me'arba amot, נידון משום לחי. lechi, Remember,
once something is longer than four אמות, amot it's no longer a
לחי, lechi, it's too big, it's like it creates its—it's like a
wall of a מבוי. mavoi A minimum size of a מבוי mavoi
is four אמות. amot. So until four אמות, amot, it counts as
a לחי lechi. ומשתמש עם חודה הפנימי. umishtamesh im chuda hapnimi. So
as long as this is up to four אמות, amot, right? And
long as it's four אמות amot and this is a לחי lechi,
and you can go until the inner side because this is assuming
that you cannot use the area opposite the לחי, lechi. only until
where the לחי lechi begins. That's if it's up to four
אמות. amot. ארבע אמות, arba amot, once it extends four אמות, amot,
נידון משום מבוי, nidon mishum mavoi, then it's no longer a לחי,
lechi, then it's a part—then it's just a part of the wall
of the מבוי. mavoi ואסור להשתמש בכולו, ve'asur lehishtamesh bechulo, and you
can't use—not only can you not use the space opposite the לחי,
lechi you can't use the מבוי Mavoy because the מבוי Mavoy. no
longer has a לחי. lechi It stops being a לחי, lechi right?
Once it gets too long, it stops being a לחי. lechi. Okay,
so that was the teaching. ואת אמרת לן עלה, ve'at amart lan
alah, and you said to us about this teaching: שמע מינה תלת.
shema mina telat. We can infer three הלכות halachot from this. שמע
מינה בין לחיים אסור. shema mina bein lechayim asur. We see that
you cannot use the space opposite the לחי lechi, because it said
even when it was less than four אמות, amot. you can only
go until the inner part of it. So you cannot use the
space opposite the לחי, lechi wrapping up a conversation from a day
or two
ago. ושמע מינה, ushma mina, you also can infer from this: משך
מבוי בארבע, meshech mavoi bearba, that a מבוי, mavuy a minimum size
of a מבוי mavuy, is four אמות Amot. because this לחי lechi
stops being a לחי lechi. and is considered a wall of a
מבוי mavuy when it hits four
אמות. Amot ושמע מינה, ushma mina, and finally you can infer: נראה
מבחוץ ושווה מבפנים נידון משום לחי. nira mibachutz veshave mibifnim nidon mishum
lechi. That as long as it's visible from the outside, even though
it's not from the inside, it counts as a לחי lechi? because
that was exactly that case, right? Visible from the outside, not as
an inside, and we're counting it as a לחי. lechi So the
first point, that you can't use the space opposite the לחי, Lechi.
was pretty much the dominant position from a day or two ago.
The other point, that a minimum size of a מבוי mavuy is
four אמות, Amot also pretty much is what we've been saying, and
a לחי Lechi stops being a לחי Lechi. when it's four אמות.
Amot. But the last point is that even though it's only visible
from the outside, it's a לחי. Lechi So what's the upshot of
this whole סוגיא? sugya? והלכתא, vehilcheta, the הלכה halacha is: נראה מבחוץ
ושווה מבפנים נידון משום לחי. nira mibachutz veshave mibifnim nidon mishum lechi.
It's visible from the outside and flush on the
inside, it counts. So actually, although we've been really trying to say
it doesn't count, it seems like we made this whole big argument,
it says that it actually does count. So the גמרא Gemara says:
תיובתא והלכתא? tiuvta vehilcheta? So, okay, now this is a good two
words. תיובתא והלכתא: tiuvta vehilcheta: a contradiction and you פסקן pasken that
way? We just got through saying that this whole case demonstrated that
the fact that it was visible from the outside didn't count, the
whole back of this courtyard was no good. And you say תיובתא,
tiuvta, contradicts that position, and now you're פסקנינג paskening that way that
it counts as a לחי? lechi. So תיובתא והלכתא? tiuvta vehilcheta? So
the גמרא Gemara says: אין, in, yeah, משום דתני רבי חייא כוותיה
mishum detani Rabbi Chiyya kevataih because although that case of the ברייתא
braita of the small חצר and big חצר was a contradiction, if
you remember yesterday we had an explicit ברייתא braita, that רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiyya taught that said explicitly whether it's visible on the outside
and not the inside or the inside and not the outside, it's
good. So end of the story is there is evidence in both
directions. So yes, this case of the two courtyards shows that it's
not good according to that ברייתא, braita, but according to that משנה—but
mishnah there's other evidence that it is good. And therefore we're going
to rule like the evidence that it does count. So that's what
we say, הלכתא. hilcheta. So we say: אין, in, yeah, that it
does count. Now that's interesting because conceptually, although obviously this got pretty
technical as it tends to do in עירובין, Eruvin, conceptually, if we
say visible from the outside is enough, it's an important point because
you would think that the whole point of a לחי is to
be, or of a קורה korah or whatever, is to be visible
to the people inside so that they don't take their objects and
walk with them and step outside with them, right? So if it's
acceptable to be visible only enough from the outside, does it say
it's not a היכר? heker? Does it say fundamentally it's because it's
functioning like a wall because it doesn't have to be visible to
the people on the inside? Or do we say somehow that yes,
it is a היכר, heker, but at the end of the day,
when חזל Chazal sort of instantiated it and quantified it, it was
sufficient that it served as a היכר heker to someone? In the
end, even if in the particular case it doesn't serve as a
היכר heker on the inside, that would be enough. And that is
interestingly the הלכה, halacha, it's enough that it's a היכר heker on
the outside.
So people of this small חצר aren't able to carry in their
courtyard, right? So then the people in the little חצר are able
to carry in their little חצר.
And according to that, yes, Michael's good point, we'd say in this
case you are not allowed to carry into because they didn't make
an עירוב, eruv, but they can carry in their courtyard. They're not
considered to be totally exposed because this is considered. to be a
לחי. That is absolutely correct. So that משנה, Mishna, in that case
we would not rule like it, only in a very special case
where the walls extend inward and you don't say לבוד everything we've
been saying. Now, so we've covered a lot of ground since the
first משנה Mishna about how a קורה Korah functions, how a לחי
functions, the space below the קורה, Korah, the space opposite the לחי.
Now we actually turn to the second clause in the משנה. Mishna.
All of that was an elaboration of the idea that if it
was too high you have to lower it, and then you know
related discussions. But if you remember the משנה Mishna also said that
if the opening of the מבוי mavuy is too big, you have
to make it smaller, right? It can't work on a space bigger
than ten אמות. Amot ורחב מעשר Verachav me'eser because ten אמות amot.
has been the number we've been saying a lot until now. If
the opening is bigger than ten אמות amot. of the מבוי ימעט,
Mavoy yima'et, you have to make the opening smaller if you want
the לחי or the קורה Korah to work. So says the גמרא,
Gemara אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, which אביי Abaye says, תנו רבנן: Tanu
Rabbanan: ורחב מעשר ימעט, Verachav me'eser yima'et, wider than ten you have
to make small. רבי יהודה אומר אינו צריך למעט. Rabbi Yehuda omer
eino tzarich lema'et.
You don't have to make it small. The same way רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says it doesn't have to be, you know, it can
be higher than twenty, here he says it can be wider than
ten. ועד כמה, Ve'ad kama, so according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
how wide can it be? You might remember back on the first
דף that we tried to learn it out from the opening of
the אולם Ulam or of the היכל Heichal which would mean that
according to you know that might sort of push us in one
direction. Here the גמרא Gemara is ignoring all of that. What would
be the limit of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, how wide could it
be? So סבר רב אחא קמיה דרב יוסף למימר, Savar Rav Acha
kamei deRav Yosef lemeimar, עד שלש עשרה אמה ושליש, Ad shelosh esre
ama ushlish, וקל וחומר מפסי ביראות, Vekal vachomer mi'pasi biraot, and you
make a קל וחומר Kal vachomer from the from the walls around
the wells. What is this? This is a special case that רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda talks about, which is
you had wells in public places that would be used, was referred
to before, that would be used when you know people would come
up to you for the רגלים Regalim or just in general. You
had wells in public places. Here's your well. Now your well is
you know ten טפחים deep and four by four wide so whatever,
it's four by four wide, it's a רשות היחיד. Reshut Hayachid. So
if I'm out here and I'm drawing my water from the well,
I'm taking it from a רשות היחיד. Reshut Hayachid. Right? And if
I'm standing here then I'm taking it from a רשות היחיד Reshut
Hayachid and if this is a רשות הרבים now when I draw
my water I'm going to be carrying, big problem. Right? So how
do you let people use the well on שבת? Shabbat? So what
you do is, if this is the well, you make, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda said we allow you to do these corners here like
this, little walls. So it looks like four walls, but it's got
huge gaps. Okay? There's more open space than there is closed space.
Something we would never allow. Normally you need there to be... we'll
see, but normally you need there to be, you know, עומד מרובה
על הפרוץ, Omed meruba al haparutz, more closed space than open space.
But we allow this so that it gives a lot of access
to people and because it frames four walls, it's okay. That's called
פסי ביראות. Pasi biraot. How big can this be? So basically the
גמרא Gemara says it can be thirteen and a third אמה. ama
The reason we come up with that size is basically it's big
enough for four cows to be going in and four cows to
be going out. You need four cows? I don't know because they
would have a group of four cows, they carry I guess they
carry the water or something anyway going in and going out. What?
Yeah, now on שבת. Shabbat. I don't know why that was the
size, anyway we'll see, but anyway but that becomes thirteen and a
third אמות. amos. So the גמרא Gemara is saying if רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda allows a gap up to thirteen and a third אמות
amos. here, that presumably would be the size of the maximum size
of the opening he would allow in a מבוי. mavuy, Okay? Yes.
What do you call that space if you created with those four
walls? It's a רשות היחיד. Reshut Hayachid. So so you've solved the
problem of the well being in a רשות היחיד Reshut Hayachid by
making the space right, sorry.
Yeah, the point is now the space around it is a רשות
היחיד Reshut Hayachid so you take from רשות היחיד Reshut Hayachid into
רשות היחיד. Reshut Hayachid.
But then you still have to walk out to the...
Oh, no, then you have to actually drink your water in that
space. Yeah, yeah, that's a problem, right. So you cannot bring the
water to the house, you can only you can only use it
essentially as a water fountain. Right. So that's a good question why
you need to bring all the cows. Maybe you need to get
give water to the cows I guess, yeah.
It's hard to drink out of
a well if you're a cow. Right, yeah, you would not spray
it out, yeah.
So the cows have gotten bigger since...
oh I don't know. Anyway let's move on.
The picture here shows Holstein cows which are very interesting because they
were from Europe. Okay, moving on.
So the
גמרא Gemara
says
like this. ומה פסי ביראות, Uma pasi biraot, what's the case by
this פסי ביראות Pasi biraot the walls around the well, שהתירתו בהן
פרוץ מרובה על העומד, She'hitartu bahen parutz meruba al ha'omed, you're very-
you're so lenient you allow even more open space than closed space,
and even though you're being very lenient, לא התירתו בהן יותר משלוש
עשרה אמה ושליש, Lo hitartu bahen yoter mishlosh esre ama ushlish, even
though you're being very lenient you don't allow... limited the size of
the openings to thirteen and a third אמות. amos. מבוי שלא התרת
בפרץ מרובה על העומד, mavuy she-lo hittarta be-paratz merubba al ha-omed, a
מבוי mavuy which you're strict, you said that obviously you cannot have
more open than closed. It needs to follow the normal rules; most
of it has to be closed. So, if you're more strict, אינו
דין שלא תתיר ביותר משלוש עשרה אמה ושליש? aino din she-lo tatte
be-yoter mi-shelosh esreh ammah u-shlish? Certainly, you shouldn't allow more than thirteen
and a third. You don't even allow it by a פסי ביראות
passi biraot which you're so lenient. So the גמרא Gemara. says, one
minute, you could say the opposite. ואי נתני, ve-i natne, what do
you mean? That exactly makes sense. פסי ביראות, passi biraot, by the
case of the well, שהתרת בהן פרץ מרובה על העומד, she-hittarta ba-hen
paratz merubba al ha-omed, you're being so lenient, you're allowing so much
space to be open. So if you're so lenient that way, you
have to draw the line somewhere. So there, לא תתיר בהן יותר
משלוש עשרה אמה ושליש, lo tatte ba-hen yoter mi-shelosh esreh ammah u-shlish,
we have to limit the size of the openings to thirteen and
a third אמות. amos, מבוי, mavuy, but a מבוי mavuy. that generally
you're not lenient, שלא התרת בהן פרץ מרובה על העומד, she-lo hittarta
ba-hen paratz merubba al ha-omed, normally you demand, you don't allow more
open than closed, you need more closed. So מבוי mavuy. where everywhere
else you're strict, there we can give you more latitude when it
comes to the size of the opening. תתיר בו יותר מי"ג אמה
ושליש, tatte bo yoter mi-yod-gimel ammah u-shlish, maybe we'll give you more
latitude to the size of the opening. So you can't learn it
out from פסי ביראות, passi biraot, right? Here, we limit it because
the whole approach is so super lenient, so we're going to limit
the size of the opening. By a מבוי mavuy, where generally we're
strict, maybe we allow the opening to be even bigger. אי נמי,
i nami, or I'll say, לאידך גיסא, le-idakh gisa, I'll go the
opposite way. פסי ביראות דאקלת בה חדא קולא, passi biraot d'akkalta beh
khada kula, אקלת בה כולא אחרינא. akkalta beh khula akhrina. Maybe like
you were trying to say: you're so lenient by a פסי ביראות,
passi biraot, be lenient here and even allow thirteen and a third.
מבוי, mavuy. but by a מבוי mavoy which maybe you have no
leniencies, everything is, you know, the strict letter of the law, כלל
כלל לא, klal klalo, maybe we don't allow anything more than ten
אמות. amos So you can't learn anything from the פסי ביראות. passi
biraot. It's a special case. Maybe we're more lenient by a מבוי,
mavoy maybe we don't even allow that much by a מבוי. mavoy.
Who knows? Whatever רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says by פסי ביראות, passi
biraot, you cannot infer what he would say by the case of
the מבוי. mavoy So the גמרא Gemara. does not have an answer
to know how far would רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda go by a
מבוי, mavoy how big would he allow the opening to be. But
we know
according to the חכמים, Chachamim, it can only be ten אמות. amos
Now the גמרא Gemara goes on, and we're going to figure out
how to solve the problem if an opening is too big. Because
if the beam is too high, it's easy to solve it: you
lower the beam, maybe you raise the floor. But if an opening
is too big, logically the only way to solve it is close
off part of the opening. But maybe you don't want to close
off part of the opening. You've got a nice big twenty אמה
ama opening; you don't want to wall in ten אמות. amos So
what are you going to do? So let's take a
look. So תני לוי, tani levi, so לוי Levi taught: מבוי שרחב
עשרים אמה, mavuy she-rachav esrim ammah, it's twenty אמה ama wide. Here's
what you do. Very simple. נועץ קנה באמצעיתו ודיו. no-etz kanna be-emtzaito
ve-dayo. You just put a post in the middle. Okay? You've got
your big, you've got your big twenty
אמה ama opening. Right? If it's twenty אמות, amos you just stick
a little post here, and then you have ten אמות amos on
each side. And then you presumably put, let's say, a קורה korah
on each side or like that and you're okay. Just stick a
post and you defined it as two ten אמה amah openings. Okay?
That's what he
said. So that's what he taught. But then it says, הוה תני
לה, hava tani lah, he taught that ברייתא, braita, ואמר לה, ve-amar
lah, and then he commented on it and he said, אין הלכה
כאותה משנה. ein halakha ke-osa mishna. We don't rule like that ברייתא,
he calls it a משנה mishna anyway. We don't rule like that.
איכא דאמרי, ika de-amri, אמר שמואל משמיה דלוי, amar shmuel mishme d'levi,
אין הלכה כאותה משנה. ein halakha ke-osa mishna. Some say that שמואל
Shmuel said in the name of לוי, Levi, we don't rule like
that. Okay. Why don't we rule like that? Because basically a principle
we're going to see is that there's so much air space on
either side, this cannot be, this doesn't have any sort of status.
It's like it's meaningless. Right? You've got big air space on either
side, it's just a little post. It's not considered enough to break
up that air space. It's like the phrase the גמרא Gemara is
going to use is
אתיא אוירא דהאי גיסא ודהאי גיסא ומבטלי. atya avira di-hai gisa ve-di-hai
gisa me-vatle. The air on this side and this side come along
and make it inconsequential, makes it as if it doesn't exist.
At some point, you know, if
you get wide enough, then it is... okay. So we have to
see how that wide enough is. So אלא היכי עביד, ela haikhi
avid, how would you solve the problem? So אמר שמואל משמיה דלוי,
amar shmuel mishme d'levi, so here's what לוי Levi's answer is in
the name of, שמואל Shmuel's name of לוי: Levi:
עושה פס גבוה עשרה, ose pas gavoha asara, you make ten טפחים
high plank. Obviously, it has to be ten טפחים high to count
as a wall. But here's what you do: במשך ארבע אמות, be-meshekh
arba amot, you make it four
אמות amos long, ומעמידו לאורכו של מבוי. u-mamido le-orkho shel mavuy. Now,
you thought we were going to say was that you have to
close it off somehow this way. Right? You have to make some
like substantial thing like that. We're going to get there. But here's
a more ingenious solution. He says you actually have it going in
like this. So it's four אמות amos deep into the מבוי. mavoy.
Okay? So not at an angle; I tried to draw it as
three directions. Okay. But it's like this. Okay? So therefore, he says,
four אמות amos is considered a wall, not a לחי. Remember we
said... So now you actually have one מבוי mavoy on this side
and one מבוי mavoy, on this side because this now defines the
wall of a מבוי. mavoys. So you have one מבוי mavoy here
of ten אמות amos and one מבוי mavoy. here of ten אמות
amos. and each one you can put a קורה. korah. Right. So
now, or- but if you were trying to make it work, right,
horizontally this way, then it loses significance because there's way too much
airspace on each side. But you're not trying to make it work
horizontally, you're making- trying to work, I don't know, vertically, whatever, lengthwise.
So then it just becomes a wall opposite this wall and therefore,
and you know, and that makes this into a separate מבוי. mavoi
Now תוספות Tosafot says you need a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach here
to go till the end in order to, in order to close
one off from the other. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say that and
תוספות Tosafot says that might not be the case. It might be
it's enough that as long as the first four אמות amos, you
defined this as a מבוי mavoi, and this as a separate מבוי,
then the fact that they're joined in the back doesn't matter. And
that is enough to define it as two separate מבוי. Okay, so
you solve the problem because rather than trying to work sort of,
you know, to along the opening of the מבוי to close off
the opening, it would have to be much bigger to be significant,
you're not closing off the opening, you're dividing it lengthwise.
What if you just rotated it and you had your wall four
אמות amos going width-wise, it wouldn't be enough?
No, we're going to talk about that in a minute. Okay, but
what this does is that this divides it lengthwise. אי נמי, Ei
nami, or another alternative is כדרב יהודה, k'deRav Yehuda, like רב יהודה.
Rav Yehuda.
דאמר רב יהודה, D'amar Rav Yehuda, and now here becomes the what
you would have normally thought. I mean, this is the most ingenious
solution, right, because you don't have to really close off the opening
of the מבוי. You just have to really create two separate- you
know, divide it lengthwise. The other solution is to close off the
opening to some degree. דאמר רב יהודה, D'amar Rav Yehuda, מבוי שרחב
חמש עשרה אמה, mavoy sherachav chamesh esrei amah, if it's fifteen אמה
amah wide, מרחיק שתי אמות ועושה פס שלש אמות. marchik shtei amos
v'oseh pas shalosh amos. You take- you make a two אמות amos
gap and then you do a three אמה amah plank. Okay? So
that is what we normally would have thought. So what you mean
here is fifteen. Obviously, you can make the same- do the same
math if it's ten. If it's fifteen, you have to close off
five אמות. amos So the simple thing is just put a five
אמה amah plank. But we're going to make life a little bit
easier on you and we're saying you don't need a five אמה
amah plank. You can do a three אמה amah plank and have
a two אמה amah gap. Not לבוד. Two אמות, amos not two
טפחים. So it's not לבוד. But the way it works is you're-
you look at this half of it, these five אמות amos. and
within these five אמות amos you say the majority of it is
walled and since the majority of it is walled it counts like
this whole section is walled. And since this whole section is walled,
you only have ten אמות Amot... that is open, that is unwalled,
and therefore you're okay. Okay, and now we're going to hone in
on this idea. If you want to wall off a section, how
much of the section do you have to wall off? Okay, and
there are two considerations. One is that of the entire section, for
the entire section we say that it be עומד מרובה על הפרוץ,
omed merubah al
haparutz, that the entire section has to be mostly walled and not
open. Okay, so here you have three over two. But the other
point is going to be for every plank, for every plank,
that plank has to be significant and not sort of, you know,
and not sort of disappear because of all of the air around
it. And that's going to be another consideration. So let's see what
that means. Okay, so here's what the גמרא Gemara says. מרחיק שתי
אמות, Marchik shtei amos,
you make two אמות Amot gap ועושה פס שלש אמות, v'oseh pas
shalosh amos, and you make a plank of three אמות. Amot... ואמאי,
V'amai, why is that enough? says the גמרא. Gemara Or why do
you have to do that much? And תוספות Tosafot says why is
that sufficient? Maybe we should require you to make smaller gaps. And
why don't you do the following?
יעשה פס אמה ומחצה, Ya'aseh pas amah u'mechtza, make a plank an
אמה ama and a half. פס
אמה ומחצה Pas amah u'mechtza ויניח שתי אמות v'yanich shtei amos and
then have a two אמות gap ויעשה פס אמה ומחצה v'ya'aseh pas
amah u'mechtza and do one and a half. So it's the same
idea of three and two, but rather than doing three and two
by big three and big two, why don't you do, I'll use
green, no, why don't you do
one and a half, two,
and one and a half? It's the same three and two, but
maybe that's better because that has like you know it sort of
has more wall spread out, so that maybe more feels like it's
sealing the place off. So why not do that? says the גמרא.
Gemara. Could you do two and three? Could it be like two
in
a little bit and like... Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara is going
to deal with those configurations. So why not do this? שמע מינה,
Shma mina,
since you're not doing this, maybe we can infer עומד מרובה על
הפרוץ משתי רוחות לא הוי עומד. omed merubah al haparutz mishtei ruchot
lo havei omed. That maybe... Maybe this isn't good. Maybe it isn't
good because each side is smaller than the gap. It's only bigger
than the gap when you combine the two sides. And maybe that's
not good. Maybe you need to do three and two so that
one side, the total amount of wall on one side is bigger
than the whole gap. Here when each wall on each side is
smaller, maybe the walls lose their significance to be considered to seal
off the place. Maybe you need a continuous amount of wall bigger
than the largest continuous gap to be considered like a sealing off
the place. Okay, so that's the question. Can you combine from the
two sides? שמע מינה עומד מרובה על הפרץ משתי רוחות לא הוי
עומד,
Shema mina omed meruba al haparatz
mishtei ruchot lo havei omed,
maybe it doesn't count. So the גמרא Gemara says no. לעולם אימא
לך הוי עומד. Le'olam eima lach havei omed. Really I'll tell you
that if you combine from the two sides to be bigger than
the gap, that's fine. ושאני הכא דאתי אוירא דהאי גיסא ואוירא דהאי
גיסא ומבטל ליה. Veshani hacha de'ati avira dehai gisa ve'avira dehai gisa
umevatel lei.
Here it's different because the air from either side comes along and
negates it. So that's why I said there are two concepts here.
One is עומד מרובה על הפרץ, Omed meruba al haparatz, which
refers to the entire sort of length. We look at the entire
length and we say is there more, is there more wall than
gap? And here is the principle of אתי אוירא דהאי גיסא
ודהאי גיסא ומבטל ליה, Ati avira dehai gisa udehai gisa umevatel lei,
which means even when we sort of, it's a more micro look.
Here what we're saying here is the problem here is not that
three don't beat out two. Three beats out two even
if
you have to add them over here. The problem here is that
this wall gets disappeared. How come this wall disappears? Because there's two
here and there's ten here. So the ten here and the two
here sort of crowd out, almost, you know, sort of overshadow this
wall. Okay. So if, for example, the wall ended here like this
and we were trying to close off that side, then I would
say fine, one and a half, one and a half, three beats
out two. Because now I can look, I look at this entire
side and three is bigger than two, even if you have to
add it from both sides. It doesn't matter says the גמרא Gemara
that you have to add it from both sides. What matters is
when you look at a particular segment of the wall, not this
segment because this segment ends with a wall here. When you look
at this segment of the wall, this gap over here makes it
disappear. So this is different than this. This looks at the entire
length you're trying to cover and says it's mostly wall. This looks
at individual segments, okay, and says does a segment lose its significance
because, because there's so much open space on both sides?
So even if you had like a wall that in width wise
was let's say four אמות... yes... but you had five אמות on
the left of it and ten אמות... exactly, exactly.
Okay. So that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. Maybe that's the problem and
that's why we didn't give that scenario. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ויעשה פס אמה, Veya'ase pas ama, so I don't get it says
the גמרא. Gemara Here's another select, scenario, suggestion. נעביד פס אמה
וירחיק אמה
ויעשה פס
אמה וירחיק
אמה ויעשה פס אמה. Na'avid pas ama veyarchik ama veya'ase pas ama
veyarchik ama veya'ase pas ama. So forget the one and a half
and the twos. Here's a
solution.
Why don't we do this?
Why don't we say one, then a gap of one, then one,
then a gap of one, then
one? Right. Then here you have the other ten. Why don't we
do this? So it's still three beating out two. Alright. And the
גמרא Gemara assumes that you wouldn't say the air on both sides
here negates because here it's equal, it's not greater than the size
of the segment. So why don't we say that this works?
So the
גמרא Gemara says, meaning
why why didn't we suggest it? The answer could be it does
work. Alright, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara maybe
the answer is it does work, but the גמרא Gemara is at
least raising the possibility. Okay, so it says like
this. שמע מינה, Shema mina, if we don't, since we didn't say
it we can infer, עומד כפרץ אסור, Omed keparatz assur, that the
problem here is is that the standing is exactly equal to the
open
space.
Now, so this is really funny because here the עומד Omed is
מרובה על הפרץ Meruba al haparatz when you add it all up.
It's three is greater than two. But if you look at any
particular segment, right, it's one is equal to one. So maybe if
we just look at each sort of segment of the wall, since
the, assuming again you don't combine, right, remember the question is do
you combine multiple segments? If you combine multiple segments it's three against
two. But if you don't combine multiple segments so it's one against
one. And maybe that's not enough. Maybe each segment has to be
larger. It's not enough that it's equal. So is that the case?
So the גמרא Gemara says can we infer that that's why it's
not good? So לעולם אימא לך... Le'olam eima lach... לעולם אימא לך
מותר. leolam eima lach mutar. Really I'll tell you that even if
you just look at each local segment, it's enough that it's equal.
So what's the problem here? Same problem as before, דשאני הכא דאתי
אוירא דהאי גיסא ודהאי גיסא ומבטלי ליה. deshani hacha deati avira dehai
gisa udehai gisa umevatli leh.
The point is
if you got yourself if the wall had ended here you'd be
okay cause each segment is equal to the size to the open
gap and that's enough, it doesn't have to be larger. The problem
is that this segment disappears because you have a larger space here
and equal here and that makes this segment disappear. There's too much
air space on both sides. Okay, so there's two issues. Regarding the
question of עומד מרובה על הפרוץ, omed meruba al haparutz, that the
whole that the entire length it has to be more. There's the
question is number one, do you say צד אחד או בשני צדדים?
tzad echad
o bishnei tzdadim? Right? Does it have to be bigger if is
it basically have to be three you know צד אחד tzad echad
means it would have to be three and two. בשני צדדים bishnei
tzdadim would be you could have one point five, two, and then
one point five. When you say it has to be bigger, can
you combine them right to be bigger than the gap? Or does
any individual length have to be bigger than the gap? That's one
question of עומד. omed. And the other question is עומד כפרוץ, omed
keparutz, right? Which is what happens when it is one and one,
right, one and one. Okay, so here you know here if you
assume you can only go by one side, you can't combine sides
and let's say that one side is equal and not larger. Okay,
so those are the two questions when you look at is the
whole section cut off. This is an issue of is there too
much air space on both sides that negate that negates you know
that negates it, which means even when you look beyond the amount
of space you're trying to cut off, when you look at this
space, maybe that makes that one disappear.
Okay, so those are the various factors that we are looking at.
Okay, okay. Wait, what are we saying then? We're not done. Okay,
so it says
וירחיק אמה ויעשה פס אמה ומחצה, veyarchik ama veyaaseh pas ama vamachetza,
וירחיק אמה ויעשה פס אמה ומחצה. veyarchik ama veyaaseh pas ama vamachetza.
It says okay but here I've got a much better solution here
which deals with gets rid of all of these problems which is
why don't you do one and a half,
one gap, one gap, and one and a half. So you have
three, you have two. There's not on each side the space is
not larger than the space, this is not larger than this, right?
This is not larger than that. That should be great. So that's
just like the three and the two, except the גמרא Gemara thinks
it's even better than the three and the two because you spread
out you know you make the gaps even smaller. So why shouldn't
this be okay? So גמרא Gemara says okay that is good. So
it says אינהי הכי נמי, inna hi hachi nami, you know what,
that is good. Why not? One and a half is bigger than
one, that should totally be fine. וכולי האי לא אטרחו רבנן. vechulei
hai lo atrachu rabanan. They didn't demand you did that. They let
you get away with one plank of three rather than having to
have two planks of one and a half each. Okay. Now the
גמרא Gemara says, so that's the end for now of this discussion
about how to spread out the walls with the air space. But
now the גמרא has another issue. וליחוש דלמא שבק פתחא רבא ועייל
בפתחא זוטא. velichush dilma shavik pitcha raba veayil bepitcha zuta. A much
different type of a question.
What have we now said you've done?
You've now made a three אמה ama wall here and this is
a two אמה ama gap. So the גמרא says why is this
good? It's good now you're going to put your קורה korah here
and you'll be happy. But why? You have a two אמה gap
here. Maybe everybody is going to just go out on the side
door. And as they go out on the side door then this
will be the main door not this, and then this and this
door doesn't have the קורה. korah. This is only good because the
door has the קורה, korah, but maybe they'll start using the side
gap and not the space in the front and that'll stop being
considered the door.
So the גמרא says maybe they'll leave the big door and go
through the side door ועייל בפתחא זוטא. veayil bepitcha zuta. So אמר
רב אדא בר מתנא amar Rav Adda bar Matna חזקה, chazaka, no,
we have it can be a pretty you know strong assumption that
where were we חזקה אין אדם מניח פתח גדול ונכנס בפתח קטן.
chazaka ein adam meniach petach gadol venichnas bepetach katan. People don't go
don't abandon a nice big door and go out on a tiny
little side door. So גמרא says really ומאי שנא מהא דרב הונא
ודרב אסי.
umai shna meha
deRav Huna udeRav Assi. You might remember back a
week ago where we spoke about a case
where if you had a מבוי and its side was broken and
you had like a little thing up here like ארבע אמות arba
amot but this was okay. But then רב הונא ורב אסי Rav
Huna veRav Assi were saying no actually it's not okay because we're
afraid that people are going to go out the side door here
under certain circumstances. So how come here we're afraid people would go
out on this like side door? and over here we're not afraid
of it. Why is it any different? So the גמרא says no,
here's the difference: התם קא ממיטלוכא, Hasam ka mamit locha, הכא לא
קא ממיטלוכא. Hacha lo ka mamit locha. There it's a shortcut.
Here it's not a shortcut. Here you're still going out the front.
So if you have to go out the front, why would you
go out a side door rather than the main door?
It's all still going straight out.
But here you can cut through a corner. So if it's a
side door, it's not on the front but it's off to the
side. It's actually a side door. So here we're afraid you'll go
out this way as a shortcut. And therefore that might take away
from this being the opening. But here when it's all on the
same face of the מבוי, it's not off, it's not a side
door, it's on the same face, we're not afraid they'll go out
the smaller opening rather than the bigger opening. Okay. That is the
end for a moment of that discussion, but now we're going to
once again look at this question about air space on both sides
negating what's sort of in the middle. תנן התם, Tanan hasam,
we taught over there in אהלות, Oholos, okay? Although actually it's not
a משנה. mishna. So anyway, so it's not exactly תנן התם. Tanan
hasam. Anyway, here's the teaching. עור האצלא, Or ha-atzla,
if you have a leather for a toilet seat. So basically what
do the leather of a toilet seat look like? Looks like this.
Okay, that's what it looked like. You put it on the seat
and you sat on it and that's where the waste went in
the middle. So the point is, this is basically a טפח tefach
by a טפח. tefach. And it is suspended over you know some
dead body or כזית ke-zayis from מת. meis. And the question is,
is it considered to be like a continuous טפח tefach that the
טומאה tumah hits it and spreads, right? Because if you have something
that's a טפח tefach by a טפח tefach and the טומאה tumah
is underneath it, a כזית ke-zayis of a dead body, it hits
it and it spreads rather than going through. Okay, so does the
hole become inconsequential or not? What would be the parameters that the
hole would be inconsequential? So let's take a look.
So both the leather ובחללו שלו uv'chalalo shello and the hole מצטרפין
בטפח, mitztarfin b'tefach, combine to make a טפח. tefach. מאי עור האצלא?
Mai or ha-atzla? What is this leather of the אצלא? atzla? אמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabba bar bar Chana
amar Rabbi Yochanan, עור כיסא של בית הכיסא. or kiso shel beis
ha-kisei. Fine, a leather that goes over a toilet seat. וכמה? V'kamah?
What are the parameters? So כי אתא רב דימי, ki ata Rav
Dimi,
when רב דימי Rav Dimi
came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר, amar, אצבעיים מכאן ואצבעיים מכאן
ואצבע רווח
באמצע. etzba'im mikan v'etzba'im mikan v'etzba revach b'emtza. Two fingerbreadths, a טפח
tefach is five normal fingers, six pinkies and four thumbs. Either way
is way of measuring a טפח. tefach. Okay, so anyway he's going
to say it is two fingers by two fingers by two fingers.
Okay, that's the way it works, an equal amount on each side.
Kind of a small toilet seat.
Yeah, it is pretty small.
Yeah, you're right, it is pretty small.
Okay, good point, I didn't actually do the math. Anyway, you're right.
So that's what he says. כי אתא רבין אמר, Ki ata Ravin
amar, now when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he
said, אצבע ומחצה מכאן ואצבע ומחצה מכאן ואצבע רווח באמצע. Etzba u-mechtza
mikan v'etzba u-mechtza mikan v'etzba revach b'emtza. He
said no, it's 1.5, 1.5, and 1 in the middle. Okay, so
those are the two versions of that. So now the גמרא says
which is even smaller. Right. So let's take a look.
אמר ליה אביי לרב
דימי, Amar lei Abaye l'Rav Dimi, so אביי Abaye said to רב
דימי, Rav Dimi, who said the 2, 2, and 2, מי פליגי?
mi peligi? Do you guys really debate? Are you arguing? אמר ליה
לא, Amar lei lo, no we're not really arguing. הא ברברבתא הא
בזוטרתא. Ha b'ravrvata ha b'zutrata. I gave this 2, 2, and 2
which equals 6 because I'm talking about six pinkies. Okay, and a
טפח tefach is six pinkies. And he gave this 1.5, 1, and
1.5 which equals 4 because he's talking about four thumbs. And four
thumbs and six pinkies are the same. It's all a טפח tefach
by a טפח. tefach. Okay, so we're not really arguing. We're all
describing different ways of attaining a טפח tefach by a טפח. tefach.
So he said, אמר ליה לא הא ברברבתא הא בזוטרתא, amar lei
lo ha b'ravrvata ha b'zutrata, whether you're talking about big fingers or
small fingers. ולא פליגין, V'lo palgin, and we're not arguing. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so אביי Abaye said back to him, לעין? La'in? Really?
פליגיתו, Pligisu, you are arguing. ובאומן ובפרץ משתי רוחות פליגיתו. U'va'uman u'va-peretz
mi-shetei ruchos palginu. You're arguing about whether you can combine the closed-off
space from both sides. He says, I don't care that they're both
a טפח. tefach. That's not what interests me today. This is one
way of measuring a טפח, tefach, this is another. What I care
about is the proportions. You're insisting that it be equal the amount
on the sides to the amount on the middle. He is insisting
that the amount on the side be bigger than the. And that's
what I think your argument is about is that you need it
that even on one side the amount of the amount of עמוד
*amud*, the amount that's not open, the closed is even from each
one side is bigger than the middle. For him, he doesn't need
it to be bigger on one side, for him it's enough that
he adds it on both sides, right? Remember this discussion we had
over here, right? Does it have to be bigger when you combine
the two sides? Or is it bigger, has to be bigger just
one section? That's what I say your argument is about. Okay? משתי
פליגותא לדידך *mishtei pligusa lididach*, according to you, הוי עמוד משתי רוחות
*havei amud mishtei ruchos*. For you, you say it's enough that you
combine the standing part on both sides and that it's bigger than
the middle. So four is bigger than two. For Ravin, Ravin who
says it's one and a half, one, and one and a half,
so for Ravin, מרוח אחת הוי עמוד משתי רוחות לא הוי עמוד
*meruach achas havei amud mishtei ruchos lo havei amud*. He says you
have to be bigger even on by one side alone. So he
needed it to be one and a half, one, and one and
a half. That's what he needed. מרוח אחת הוי עמוד משתי רוחות
לא הוי עמוד *meruach achas havei amud mishtei ruchos lo havei amud*.
אי סלקא דעתך לא פליגיתו *isalka daitach lo pligitu*, if you guys
really aren't arguing, לרבין הכי בעי ליה למימר *l'ravin hachi ba'ei lei
l'meimar*, then even if he's using a unit that equals four, if
he really agreed with you, he should have said אצבע ושליש מכאן
ואצבע ושליש מכאן ואצבע ושליש רווח באמצע *etzba ushlish mikan ve'etzba ushlish
mikan ve'etzba ushlish revach be'emtsa*. He should have said one and a
third, one and a third, one and a third, right? Saying, it's
not interesting to me that this equals four, what's interesting is that
he divides it differently. Here everything is equal, and here he made
sure that each side was bigger than the middle. If he really
said the same, he should have said one and a third, one
and a third, one and a third. That would have made everything
equal and would have got four. So you see you guys really
are arguing. Okay, so he said, ואלא מאי *ve'ella mai*, so then,
he said back to Abaye, Rav Dimi said back to Abaye. So
what do you think? פליגינן *pliginon*, we're arguing? So לדידי הכי בעי
לי למימר *lididi hachi ba'ei li l'meimar*, if I really felt you
could combine both sides to be bigger than the middle, then I
should have said a bigger חידוש *chiddush*. I should have said אצבע
ושני שלישים מכאן ואצבע ושני שלישים מכאן ואצבע ושני שלישים רווח באמצע
*etzba ushnei shlishim mikan ve'etzba ushnei shlishim mikan ve'etzba ushnei shlishim revach
be'emtsa*. Right? Here it's not so obvious that the reason this works
is because two plus two is four is greater than two, right?
If that was the point that you could combine the sides, I
should have said a much bigger point. I should have said one
and a third, one and a third, and what is it? Two
and two thirds, something like that. One and two thirds, what'd he
say? אצבע ושני שלישים *etzba ushnei shlishim*? Yeah, three and a third
and this would have been two and two thirds. Okay. Meaning this
case, each side would have been less than the middle and it
still would have worked. If I really wanted to say you could
have combined, I would have given the example where each side would
have been less than the middle. I didn't give that example. I
gave the example where each side was equal to the middle. If
that's what's true, it's not based on combining the two sides. So
אלא אי איכא למימר דפליגינן *ella ee ika l'meimar d'pliginon*, if we're
debating, it's not that I'm saying you combine the two sides, but
בפרוץ כעומד פליגי *be'parutz k'omed pligi*. It's because I would actually say
you don't combine the two sides, but still, two is equal to
two. It doesn't have to be greater than two. Okay, he says
it has to be greater, I say it's enough that it's equal.
So that as I said is when you say פרוץ *parutz* that
the עומד *omed* has to be מרובה על הפרוץ *merubbah al haparutz*,
there's two ways you can do it to be lenient. One is
you can say you can combine the two sides, one and a
half plus one and a half is greater than two. That's one
way, as opposed to saying it has to be on just one
side bigger, three and two. Okay, that's what we first started saying
is that you combine the two sides. And he says no, I
actually be strict and will say you can only look, any independent
side has to be bigger. But even there the question is does
it have to be bigger, one and a half is bigger than
one, or is it enough that it's equal, two is equal to
two. So if we're debating, it's not because I'm saying you combine
the sides, I'm saying you look at each side, but I don't
say it has to be bigger, I say it's enough that it's
equal. Okay and with that we'll stop for now. What do we
really think the whole ענין *inyan* of הלכות טומאה *halachas tumah* has
anything, any bearing? I was about to... so that is a very
good question why we think it's relevant and you know תוספות *Tosafot*
actually points out to that that like how we define issues of
מחיצה *mechitza* are not necessarily the same way we define whether it's
considered to be containing.